Privilege escalation is a bug class that comes in a lot of variations and to know
best what we should focus on I did the case study of 162 public bug bounty
reports and in this video I will show you which ones get the highest bounties.
Enjoy! So I have nine different groups of what the attacker was able to do with
the attack and we'll go through them one by one starting with the most common one
which was reading victims data. It was the backlash that it's kind of overlaps
with IDORs but because I already have done the IDOR case study I tried to
focus on a bit different things in this case study. As the example I have this
report by Yousef Samouda from Facebook where there was a free request process
to upload the file and these are always always interesting because when you
have your data in the system it's stored in some kind of database where it's
tied to to your user ID and it's it's still possible to make a mistake and
and have the IDOR there but it's way harder to do something secure with files
because files they don't have metadata. Files only have the file name and the
file content and that's usually it. So any request that handles files is
interesting especially like here we had one request where the user would upload
the file to a CDN then in the response they would get the video ID then in the
second request they would exchange the video ID for some other identifier that
looks like this and then there is the third request which connects the
uploaded file uploaded video with the with the user's profile and in these
types of requests of course in the first one you should always try different
things with the file path, path traversals and stuff like this but this
second and third one here always try to see if you can access other users file
ID especially if it's a predictable one and in this case the second
request was probably secure because it's not mentioned in the blog post but
in the third one Yousef could just exchange the video ID for another user's
ID and then other file would be appended to normal user's profile would be
normally shown on the user's profile in this case I think Yousef appended some
kind of internal crash log screenshot and he was rewarded twelve and a half
thousand dollars bounty by Facebook. Now some of these reports will be similar to
IDERS but because I think every single IDER is a kind of privilege escalation
bug I did not want to include them again because I already did IDER case study so
keep this in mind when looking at these statistics. The next group that that we
have is creating or modifying resources with only one less report but a lot
higher bounty which is kind of interesting because it is not due to the
fact that creating or modifying resources is by CVSS more impactful
because if we take a look at CVSS this is the typical setting that you would
use for any kind of IDER so this would be for creating or modifying
resources and this would be for reading and both have the rating of seven and a
half so CVSS wise there is no difference in the impact between these two groups
but in practice we can see that there is a clear difference in in the average
bounty maybe it's because of the fact that if you can modify or create
resources likely you can at least partially read something so then the
impact increases but one way or another it's always worth to look for the
bugs in all the possible actions of creating and reading as well and I have
this report by Teddy Katz as the as a great example this one was in GitHub and
yeah systems that maintain version control are especially interesting
because of how commits work I won't go into the detail of how this particular
report worked the TLDR is that a Teddy could add himself as the maintainer to
somebody else's repository but the thing I want to mention about about these
systems is when you have a target that works with files from one particular
repository from one particular organization it may seem that it is
secure because they will not pull files from your repository but if you control
the commit hash know that if you fork the repository and create a commit on
your fork and never merge this fork never make a pull request the commit
will be available on the main repository using the same hash that's how how git
works and this is this is the feature not the bug and developers that create
that create some apps forget about this and they do not know that that if you
control the commit hash you kind of control the whole the whole repository
because you can then just pull your own fork with whatever you want inside so
keep this in mind we're testing for for anything that works with with git when
you control the the commit hash then the the next group is permanently escalate
permissions within the organizations so these are the attacks where the attacker
is somebody that's inside the organization but they have low
privileges and by executing the attack they can escalate their privileges to
admin to manager whatever the role is and these attacks are that much
impactful that the two previous groups they were only working for one
particular request you could read one thing or modify one thing and if you
elevate your permissions from now on you have elevated permissions and you
can do anything that the admin can do so most of the time if we take a look at
CVSS most of the time you will be confidentiality and integrity high but
because you have to be part of the organizations you will have privileges
required low or in some cases even high it is very dependent if you can escalate
from let's say admin to owner that's privileges required high but one way or
another these attacks are are definitely great and we have 30 reports so this is
a common problem and most of these were happening inside the functionality of
organization or user management so these are quite it's good to test for them
because you just have these functionalities that you have to audit
it's not like you have to see every single request and before somebody ask
in the comments you can access this database in the BBRE premium archive
that's linked in the description the example I have is very very simple
attack in Facebook you just have this request and analyst can elevate their
permissions to admin you just use your own user ID, ad account ID, permission ID
and that's it and a lot of privilege escalations look simple but the real
value that the hunter did was just browsing the app auditing a lot of
endpoints seeing which ones are secure and then all of a sudden finding the
vulnerable one and then report is often as simple as this one but yeah the real
value is outside of this write-up so don't be fooled that it's so easy to
look for for privilege escalations the next group that we have is deleting
resources which sort of completes our four actions that you can do with the
object create, read, update, delete and there are fewer reports than the two
previous groups but I still think you should spend a lot of time testing for
deleting resources the first reason is it is less obvious as the less
experienced version of me I used to kind of ignore the delete actions because I
thought there is very little impact if we take a look at CVSS again keep in
mind that if you can delete a resource there's not an availability impact
availability refers to availability of the system and not availability of the
data which means even if you can delete all the data in the system
availability impact is none. Deleting data is integrity impact so CVSS wise
you're in the same sort of bracket as updating or creating resources of course
if what you can delete is is not very sensitive it's maybe integrity low or it
might even be a non qualifying vulnerability but in other systems it
will be maybe even more dangerous than than other actions and one other aspect
why I think this deleting is you're more likely to find it especially in hardened
targets is because it's harder to test for because if you have the read action
it's fairly easy to automate this you can do it with authorize you can write
your own script that just has the IDs of different objects you just send the
request from a different session and that's pretty much the check done. When
you have updating or creating is a bit harder because you need the proper body
of the request and even if you can automate some fetching from JavaScript
or by whatever other means you can enumerate names of the parameters
likely will still not know what are the values of those parameters so it's
harder to automate this and deleting I would say is even a little bit harder
because if you send a request from the original session you cannot replay
replay this this request from the attacker session because the object is
already deleted so we need to find another one and these things even though
if you're just testing you know one resource is not a problem to do this but
if you think about you know multiplying this process times 300 endpoints 400
endpoints 1000 endpoints that's a lot so that's why there's definitely more
privilege escalation bugs and iders in those actions that modify something than
in the read and especially if you have GraphQL it is possible that you can not
only delete the data but also read it at the same time in this example you could
just delete it but when you have a GraphQL mutation that looks like this
here you ask the system about what it should return in the response after
deleting the object and here is just error so this is only deleting the
resource but in some cases you will also be able to see the contents of the
object that you just deleted so then you have both the confidentiality and
integrity impacts so yeah when you have when you have GraphQL always pay even
more attention than normally to deleting objects even if they are they may not be
sensitive to delete if you're able to read them that's definitely sensitive so
pay attention to to this the next group is something interesting because I've
never actually tested for this at least I haven't spent a lot of time testing
for this it's when the attacker keeps their or their old privileges so the
attack scenario is that the attacker already has some privileges in the
application but it's impossible for the legitimate user to to remove the attacker
from the organization or remove attackers permissions so sometimes it's
it's as simple as just the session token not being invalidated for for a long
time where the attacker can refresh it over and over again but we also have a
very interesting report here in reddit where the hunter 41bin found something
that seems like not something severe they found a way to create the user that
would be hidden from the user list and probably it's something that I wouldn't
even report I would probably brush it off as maybe a low-risk vulnerability
that the company will not reward or at least not reward well but the attack
scenario that the hunter came up with is to as the attacker that already is the
admin organization create another admin in the same organization but the one
that's hidden so then when let's say in the real world the attacker leaves the
company and the company the user with the owner permission wants to remove
them from the organization on reddit or on reddit ads in this case they remove
the attacker but because the hidden user created by the attacker is not is not
visible to the to the owner the hidden user is not deleted and of course the
attacker has credentials to this account so they can keep those permissions
forever and it's also kudos to to reddit here because they rewarded it $5,000 as a
high and I want to appreciate it because I feel that sometimes even though we say
in bug bounty impact is the king I still feel that often it's hard to get paid
well for something that's not a standard vulnerability when you do something
that's out of the box or something that doesn't have a back class name or
something like this it's harder to get this through triage and it's harder to
get this paid well even if the impact is there just because it's non-standard but
it's not the case here here reddit took a look at it at the impact standpoint
not at the backlash standpoint and they rewarded it fairly so so well well done
reddit then joining another organization and you can see that there is way way
fewer reports of this type 9 versus 30 of escalating privileges within the
organization so even though joining another organization is more risky and
you can even see the average bounty is way higher than than other back classes
here even though it's a small small sample size is the best we can get but
take it with a grain of salt but you can see that it is not as easy to perform an
attack that allows you to join another organization now why is the average
bounty so high that's probably because there are four Shopify reports rewarded
in total over 65k and also $35,000 of Facebook reports and the ones in
Shopify there are a few reports by Ron Chand that are kind of related I covered
them on my channel you can see them the link is in the description just if you
watch it remembered it's it's one of the first videos on my channel so you will
see how much the quality of the videos have improved but I still recommend you
to watch it because this chain is incredible it's a race condition where
with the email confirmation process where Ron was able to confirm another
email by changing it at the correct time and specifically in Shopify
bypassing email confirmation allow you to take over the the whole shop so it is
a big thing and if I think three of these reports in total that I covered
were rewarded $37,000 so yeah it's it's definitely something to to pay
attention to next we have paywall bypasses and it's a backlash that I was
very curious about because it's not something that I test a lot and I wanted
to see if I should and to be honest if anything this case study convinced me
that I shouldn't spend a lot of time here we have only seven reports in this
group and they are not really rewarded that well we can see two reports
rewarded $2,000 from Shopify which doesn't sound bad but it's still
rewarded as a low and I imagine a lot of companies just didn't accept them at all
so yeah to sum it up it's not something that that I'm gonna be spending my time
on then the next group that that's kind of named a bit strangely bypassing
victims confirmation it's it's attacks where I wasn't really able to determine
the immediate impact an example we have here in slack where if you invite
somebody to the slack workspace they have to accept the invitation and you
could bypass this accepting the invitation so you could invite the
victim to the workspace and have them automatically accept the invitation by I
think changing their role immediately so there's no immediate impact to this
because it's the victim joining your slack workspace but because there is the
confirmation it is there for some reason so some companies will will pay for this
if you can bypass that it's probably not something I'm gonna spend a lot of time
on as well but it's something to be aware of that if there is a confirmation it
might be there for a reason and in some cases we might not even understand the
business impact and the real implications so yeah keep this keep this
in mind and finally the last group which for me is a very important one because
it's not something that I used to test for and I probably will start from now
on oath app that has too many privileges and I'm if you know me you know that I
love oath it's probably the first functionality that I test on every
target but these scenarios it's not something that I really considered so
what happens here is when you log into example.com with your Twitter account in
this example you are being shown this consent screen and when you authorize
the app what happens on the backend the app the example.com gets the access
token with which it can communicate with the Twitter API and fetch some
information about you modify some information on your behalf and do other
actions and exact actions are being shown on this consent screen so here it
clearly says what the application can and cannot do and the attack scenario
here is that this access token that the application has actually can do the
actions that this screen says it mustn't so the access token allowed the
app to access person's direct messages while the the permission for this was
not given on the consent screen and Twitter rewarded this three thousand
dollars almost three thousand dollars and it's interesting for me because it's
kind of hard to test because you have to create your own application which also
means you're limited to targets that allow to do this so it's like Facebook
Twitter Google and other big applications that allow to use
themselves as authorization server to log into other websites and the attack
scenario is that you have to create the app and go through the flow and fetch
the token and a lot of people just won't do it so they won't test for this
scenario and this is this is one case that can happen that the token has too
many privileges compared to what was shown on the consent screen but it gets
even better here we have a github report from Tanner which was even better because
the application to which you granted permissions had more permissions than
the user giving the permission so the attack scenario changes here
significantly because now the user can just create their own application in the
organization and all of a sudden this user's application has more permissions
than the user themselves so it's a normal privilege escalation inside the
organization and that's why this scenario is is more dangerous because
at the end of the day the user can just escalate their privileges
but the the sort of way to do it is very creative and it's probably not
something that a lot of people test for and in this case it was rewarded
ten thousand dollars so a really really nice attack and definitely something for
me to add to my to my testing methodology and that's it these are all
the groups that I have prepared for you today if you want to see the full case
study it's available in the BBRE Premium Archive and if you enjoyed listening
about privilege escalations check out this episode of the podcast that I
recorded with Douglas Day who's the absolute best hunter when it comes to
looking for privilege escalations the link is on the screen right now and in
the description and for now thank you so much for watching and goodbye